<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Working With Charts</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Working With Charts">
            <p>*** Note: The <a href="../tags/name.html">name tag page</a> has an example about how
            to use Name tags to change named ranges' formulas dynamically with JETT formulas,
            indirectly updating a chart's data ranges.</p>
            <p>Neither JETT nor Apache POI has an API to create a chart dynamically.  However, both
            preserve features such as charts if found in the template spreadsheet.  For charts to
            work in JETT, the chart must be created in the template spreadsheet.  JETT won't
            actually do anything to the chart; it will only populate the data that the chart will
            use.  Without the data in the template spreadsheet, certain steps must be taken to
            ensure proper display of the data in the chart in the resultant spreadsheet.</p>
            <p>If the number of rows of data to display is known before transformation, then the
            chart can simply refer to the data cells that are known to be populated in the
            resultant spreadsheet.</p>
            <p>In this example, it is known that there are 4 employees.  The bar graph's data
            ranges are already entered.  The x-axis values are $A$2:$A$5, and the only series is
            $B$2:$B$5.  The "fixed" flag is set to <code>true</code> on the
            <a href="../tags/forEach.html">forEach tag</a>, so that no shifting will occur for
            anything below the data.</p>
            <img src="../images/template_chart1.gif" alt="Template Spreadsheet 1"/>
            <p>...which gets transformed into...</p>
            <img src="../images/result_chart1.gif" alt="Result Spreadsheet 1"/>
        </section>
        <section name="Dynamic Ranges">
            <p>It is possible to use charts even when the number of rows of data is not known
            beforehand.  Normally, chart ranges are hard-coded into the template spreadsheet with a
            formula such as "Sheet1!$B$2:$B$5".  But with the Excel formulas "OFFSET" and "COUNTA",
            and the Excel "defined names" feature, it is possible for chart range formulas to refer
            to a dynamic range of data.  For Excel 2007+, look in the "Formulas" toolbar, then
            choose "Define Name".  Enter any name, e.g. "DataLabels", plus the formula.</p>
            <source>
                =OFFSET(Sheet1!$B$2, 0, 0, COUNTA(Sheet1!$B$2:$B$40), 1)
            </source>
            <p>The Excel OFFSET formula produces a range of cells, whose top-left cell is the first
            cell argument.  The range is translated by the next two arguments, which are the number
            of rows and columns.  The range height and width are the next two columns.  Here, the
            height is specified by a formula, resulting from the count of the values, and the width
            is one.  Note that here, the values should not go beyond row 40 -- the "COUNTA" formula
            cuts off the data there.  Then, the chart data simply refers to the defined name:
            "=Sheet1!DataLabels".</p>
        </section>
        <section name="Using the Name Tag">
            One can make the ranges dynamic by creating named ranges to be used by the chart and
            using <a href="../tags/name.html">name tags</a> to provide JETT formulas to the named
            ranges.
        </section>
    </body>
</document>