<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Change Log for JETT</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="JETT 0.5.0 (Beta) Released - 19 Feb 2013">
            <p>New in JETT 0.5.0:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The <a href="tags/style.html">style tag</a> has a new attribute: "class" for
                    assigning styles to a block of cells defined in a ".css" file, which is very
                    much like a CSS file in web design.</li>
                <li>If the <a href="tags/style.html">style tag</a> is used extensively, then JETT's
                    performance suffers.  Now, JETT maintains caches for styles and fonts used,
                    for easy, fast lookup and reuse.</li>
                <li>Additional test cases have been added to the JUnit test case that tests the
                    <a href="tags/hyperlink.html">hyperlink</a> tag.</li>
                <li>Bug fix: When cell borders were used in the same cell as a
                    <a href="tags/span.html">span tag</a>, the borders were not changed to match
                    the new merged region.  Now, the borders are changed to match the new merged
                    region.</li>
                <li>Bug fix: When an expression contains the method call "size()" on a collection,
                    JETT didn't properly recognize that the collection expression shouldn't be
                    processed with <a href="collections/implicit.html">implicit collections
                    processing</a>, i.e. one block for every collection item.  Now JETT properly
                    recognizes the "size()" method on a collection and doesn't perform implicit
                    collections processing in this case.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="JETT 0.4.0 (Beta) Released - 29 Nov 2012">
            <p>New in JETT 0.4.0:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>New tag: <a href="tags/style.html">"style"</a> to dynamically change the style
                on the Cells in the body of the tag, e.g.
                <code>&lt;jt:style style="font-weight: bold;font-height-in-points: 20"&gt;${expr}&lt;/jt:style&gt;</code>.</li>
                <li>New tag: <a href="tags/formula.html">"formula"</a> to dynamically create Excel
                formulas unaffected by JETT formula processing.</li>
                <li>New attributes on the <a href="tags/agg.html">"agg"</a> tag to support rollups,
                cubes, and grouping sets.</li>
                <li>New attribute on the <a href="tags/span.html">"span"</a> tag to make an
                adjustment to the size of a merged region, adding a number to the size.</li>
                <li>A new POI bean is exposed: "cell" that represents the <code>Cell</code> that
                contains the expression.</li>
                <li>One can now reference static Java methods in JEXL directly, e.g.
                <code>${java.lang.String.format("%d / %d", numerator, denominator)}</code></li>
                <li>New JETT functionality presented as registered functions, e.g.
                <code>${jett:cellRef(1, 2)} => "C2"</code>, and
                <code>${jett:cellRef(1, 2, 2, 2)} => "C2:D3"</code>.</li>
                <li>Bug fix: If an expression was repeated more than once, and is present with
                other expresssions in a Cell, then the value replacement wasn't working right.
                This is now fixed.</li>
                <li>Bug fix: Boolean values were being populated as the strings "true" and "false".
                Now they are properly populated as the Excel boolean values <code>TRUE</code> and
                <code>FALSE</code>.  Boolean expressions within strings will still yield "true"
                and "false".</li>
                <li>Lots of JUnit test cases have been added for all the new features.</li>
                <li>There is a new "readme.txt" file.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="JETT 0.3.0 (Beta) Released - 26 Sep 2012">
            <p>New in JETT 0.3.0:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><code>TagListeners</code> may now be created, which get called when any tag
                is finished processing.  All <code>Tags</code> that subclass <code>BaseTag</code>
                now support the <code>onProcessed</code> attribute for specifying
                <code>TagListeners</code>.</li>
                <li><code>TagLoopListeners</code> may now be created, which get called when every
                loop of a looping tag (<code>Tags</code> that subclass <code>BaseLoopTag</code>)
                is finished processing.  All <code>Tags</code> that subclass
                <code>BaseLoopTag</code> now support the <code>onLoopProcessed</code> attribute for
                specifying <code>TagLoopListeners</code>.</li>
                <li>There are 2 new attributes for <a href="tags/forEach.html">forEach</a> tags:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><code>groupBy</code> supports separating the collection into separate
                    groups with identical properties for further processing.</li>
                    <li><code>orderBy</code> supports ordering the collection items before
                    displaying them.</li>
                </ul>
                <li>For <a href="collections/implicit.html">Implicit Collections Processing</a>,
                4 additional metadata keys are added:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><code>indexVar</code> supports a zero-based looping variable name that
                    works just like the same-named attribute on the
                    <a href="tags/multiForEach.html">multiForEach</a> tag.</li>
                    <li><code>limit</code> supports a limit to the number of collection items
                    processed that works like the same-named attribute on the
                    <a href="tags/multiForEach.html">multiForEach</a> tag.</li>
                    <li><code>onProcessed</code> supports <code>TagListeners</code> just the same
                    as all <code>BaseTags</code> do.</li>
                    <li><code>onLoopProcessed</code> supports <code>TagLoopListeners</code> just
                    the same as all looping tags do.</li>
                </ul>
                <li>A bug was fixed in Formulas processing.  If a JETT formula is specified in
                the middle of a Cell's text, because tag text preceded it, JETT will no longer
                throw an uncaught Exception.</li>
                <li>Lots of JUnit test cases have been added for all the new features.</li>
                <li>This is the first JETT release to be submitted to the Sonatype OSS Maven
                Repository, which will make JETT available in the Maven Central Repository.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="JETT 0.2.0 (Beta) Released - 08 Aug 2012">
            <p>New in JETT 0.2.0:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>New tags: <a href="tags/comment.html">"comment"</a> to create Excel Comments on
                Cells, <a href="tags/group.html">"group"</a> to define Excel Groups (Outlines), and
                <a href="tags/hyperlink.html">"hyperlink"</a> to create Hyperlinks on Cells.</li>
                <li>It is now possible to create Excel Groups (Outlines) on dynamically placed data
                using <a href="tags/looping.html">looping tags</a> such as the
                <a href="tags/forEach.html">forEach tag</a>.  It is also possible to specify new
                metadata to create Excel Groups using <a href="collections/implicit.html">Implicit
                Collections Processing</a>.</li>
                <li>JETT has supported Rich Text using Expressions, but now it supports Rich Text
                inside certain appropriate tag attributes that are used as actual Cell contents.</li>
                <li>It is now possible to supply <a href="misc/jexl_settings.html">custom functions</a>
                into a custom JEXL namespace, which can result in such Expressions as
                <code>${custom:method(param)}</code>.</li>
                <li>Additional convenience "transform" methods in the <code>ExcelTransformer</code>
                class allow the developer to specify input and output filenames, and to let JETT
                handle the reading and writing of the Excel files.</li>
                <li>Lots of JUnit test cases have been added for all the new features, and for lots
                of old features that needed them.</li>
                <li>Two bugs are fixed relating to JETT Formulas.  One bug did not pick up the cell
                reference if it was at the end of the JETT Formula, and another bug did not allow
                negative default values to be supplied in a formula cell reference.  Both bugs are
                now fixed.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="JETT 0.1.0 (Beta) Released - 20 Jul 2012">
            <p>This is the initial release of JETT.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>