<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>PageBreak Tag</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The PageBreak Tag">
            <p>During transformation, Page Breaks may created using the "pageBreak" tag.  This tag
                must be bodiless.  Excel page breaks may be created horizontally below the tag cell
                or vertically to the right of the tag cell.  It is possible to create both or
                neither on the same cell.</p>
            <p>Use the optional "display" attribute to display the contents of the cell, if any.</p>
            <h1>Attributes</h1>
            <ul>
                <li>The "pageBreak" tag supports all <a href="basics.html">base tag attributes</a>.</li>
                <li><strong>type: String</strong> Required.  Create an Excel Page Break on the row
                    below or the column to the right of the cell.  Here are the possible values:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><em>rows</em> Create a horizontal Excel Page Break below this cell.</li>
                    <li><em>cols</em> Create a vertical Excel Page Break to the right of this cell.</li>
                    <li><em>both</em> Create a horizontal Excel Page Break below this cell <em>and</em>
                        a vertical Excel Page Break to the right of this cell.</li>
                    <li><em>none</em> Do not create any Excel Page Break here.</li>
                </ul>
                <li><strong>display: RichTextString</strong> Optional.  This determines the contents
                    of the cell.  The default is blank.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Example">
            <p>In this example, horizontal and vertical Excel Page Breaks are created.  One tag
                creates both on one cell.</p>
            <img src="../images/template_pagebreak.gif" alt="Page Break Template"/>
            <p>After transformation, horizontal and vertical Excel Page Breaks have been created.
                Notice that on cell C3, both a horizontal and a vertical break are created.  Also
                notice that on cell I9, no page breaks are created.  The break between columns H
                and I was created by the tag on H4, and the break between rows 8 and 9 was created
                by the tag at D8.</p>
            <img src="../images/result_pagebreak.gif" alt="Page Break Result"/>
            <p>When opening a JETT-created spreadsheet with page breaks created, the page breaks
                may not be visible until after viewing a Print Preview in Excel.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>