<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Comment Tag</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The Comment Tag">
            <p>During transformation, Excel Comments may be created by using the "comment" tag.
            This tag must be used in the bodiless form.  When processed, the "comment" tag creates
            a new Excel Comment on the Cell.</p>
            <p>In the internal Apache POI library's API, the method "createDrawingPatriarch" is
            called in order to create the Comment.  On older Excel spreadsheets (.xls, versions
            97-2003), this appears to corrupt other existing drawings such as shapes and charts.
            However, on newer Excel spreadsheets (.xlsx, versions 2007+), this leaves existing
            drawings such as shapes and charts intact.</p>
            <h1>Attributes</h1>
            <ul>
                <li><strong>value: RichTextString</strong> Required.  This becomes the contents of
                the actual Cell to which the Excel Comment is attached.  Rich Text String
                formatting is respected.</li>
                <li><strong>author: String</strong> Required.  This is the "author" portion of the
                Excel Comment.</li>
                <li><strong>comment: RichTextString</strong> Required.  This is the contents of the
                Excel Comment.  Rich Text String formatting is respected.</li>
                <li><strong>visible: boolean</strong> Optional.  This determines whether the Excel
                Comment will be initially visible.  If <code>false</code>, then the viewer must
                mouse-over the Cell to view the Comment.  The default is <code>false</code>.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Example">
            <p>In this example, Bugs Bunny comments on Elmer Fudd's line.  Notice how Rich Text
            String formatting is preserved for both the Cell contents and the Comment contents.</p>
            <p>Here is the template spreadsheet:</p>
            <img src="../images/template_comment.gif" alt="Comment Template"/>
            <p>.. gets transformed into...</p>
            <img src="../images/result_comment1.gif" alt="Comment Result"/>
            <p>When the viewer places the mouse over the Cell, the Comment pops up.</p>
            <img src="../images/result_comment2.gif" alt="Comment Mouseover"/>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>