<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Group Tag</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The Group Tag">
            <p>During transformation, Excel Groups (Outlines) may created using the "group" tag.
            This tag must be used with a body.  Excel Groups may be created on the rows from the
            body of the tag or on the columns from the body of the tag.  It is possible to nest
            "group" tags.  Excel will display nested group outlines.</p>
            <p>If the number of rows or columns to be grouped is dynamic, then it is best to use
            a <a href="looping.html">looping tag</a>.  Looping tags support the same attributes as
            the "group" tag, but it groups rows or columns on the transformed rows or columns, the
            number of which is determined dynamically.</p>
            <h1>Attributes</h1>
            <ul>
                <li>The "group" tag supports all <a href="basics.html">base tag attributes</a>.</li>
                <li><strong>groupDir: String</strong> Required.  Create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the
                resultant rows or columns.  Here are the possible values:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><em>rows</em> Create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the resultant
                    rows.  This is the default.</li>
                    <li><em>cols</em> Create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the resultant
                    columns.</li>
                    <li><em>none</em> Do not create an Excel Group (Outline).</li>
                </ul>
                <li><strong>collapse: boolean</strong> Optional.  This determines whether the Excel
                Group (Outline) created is in a collapsed state.  The default is <code>false</code>
                (not collapsed).</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Example">
            <p>In this example, Excel Groups (Outlines) of rows and columns are created.  One row
            group and one column group is nested.</p>
            <p>Along the top of the template, adjacent cells obscure each other's contents, so here
            is the content of the first row of cells:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><strong>E1:</strong> &lt;jt:group groupDir="cols"&gt;Col1</li>
                <li><strong>F1:</strong> &lt;jt:group groupDir="cols"&gt;Col2</li>
                <li><strong>G1:</strong> Col3&lt;/jt:group&gt;</li>
                <li><strong>H1:</strong> Col4&lt;/jt:group&gt;</li>
                <li><strong>I1:</strong> (empty)</li>
                <li><strong>J1:</strong> &lt;jt:group groupDir="cols" collapse="true"&gt;Col1</li>
                <li><strong>K1:</strong> Col2</li>
                <li><strong>L1:</strong> Col3&lt;/jt:group&gt;</li>
                <li><strong>M1:</strong> Show me!!!</li>
            </ul>
            <img src="../images/template_group.gif" alt="Group Template"/>
            <p>After transformation, Excel Groups (Outlines) have been created.  Notice that
            columns J, K, and L are hidden due to the collapsed column group, and that rows 12-14
            are also hidden due to the collapsed row group.</p>
            <img src="../images/result_group.gif" alt="Group Result"/>
            <p>The viewer can click on the "+" signs in Excel to expand the group, and on the "-"
            signs to collapse the group.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>