<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Welcome to JETT</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="News">
            <p><strong>JETT 0.10.0 (Beta) Released</strong></p>
            <p>New in JETT 0.10.0:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Ticket #56: Rich text strings using the "automatic" Excel color crashes JETT.
                    Now, JETT takes into account the "automatic" Excel color to avoid the crash.</li>
                <li>Ticket #57: Two or more levels of nested forEach tags with a JETT Formula that
                    refers to cells at least 2 levels deeper than the formula result in an
                    incorrect Excel formula.  There was a problem in the algorithm that JETT relied
                    upon to keep track of cell updates across 2 or more levels of nested looping
                    tags.  The formula nesting level is now kept track in the <code>TagContext</code>
                    object, and this bug is fixed.</li>
                <li>Ticket #58: A "&lt;" character inside a JETT Formula triggers a
                    <code>TagParseException</code> when the <code>TagParser</code> attempts to
                    parse it as a tag.  Now JETT skips over JETT Formula text when scanning cell
                    text looking for tags.</li>
                <li>Ticket #60: Excel 2007+ (.xlsx) templates with Excel comments in them cause
                    JETT to crash when it is cacheing pre-existing fonts when it first reads the
                    spreadsheet.  An unexpected color index, 81, was outside the normal range of
                    Excel indexed colors, causing the crash.  JETT now takes into account this
                    index to avoid the crash.</li>
                <li>Ticket #65: Using a lot of span tags, especially in a loop, causes an
                    <code>IllegalStateException</code> from Apache POI because the maximum number
                    of cell styles was exceeded.  This was caused because JETT didn't cache the new
                    <code>CellStyle</code> objects, resulting in an excessive number of similar or
                    identical cell styles.  The span tag is now caching any new cell styles it
                    creates, so it can find that same existing cell style later.</li>
                <li>Ticket #67: Create a tag that can supply a dynamic image to the resultant
                    spreadsheet.  JETT now has the <a href="tags/image.html">image tag</a>.</li>
                <li>JETT is now tested using Apache POI 3.14.  JETT now requires Apache POI 3.14
                    (or greater).</li>
            </ul>
            <p>View a history of all changes at the <a href="changelog.html">Change Log</a>.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="Overview">
            <p>JETT (Java Excel Template Translator) is a Java 5.0 API that allows speedy creation
            of Excel spreadsheet reports using Excel spreadsheet templates.</p>
            <p>JETT is built on top of the <a href="http://poi.apache.org/">Apache POI</a> library,
            which gives almost total control to the developer over the reading, creation, and
            modification of Excel spreadsheets.  This includes the very tedious, verbose, and
            error-prone process of coding cell and text formatting, including font, color,
            highlighting, borders, alignment, header/footer, etc.</p>
            <p>JETT is also built on top of the <a href="http://commons.apache.org/jexl/">Apache
            Commons JEXL library</a> (Java Expression Language), which allows expressions to be
            evaluated easily.</p>
            <p>Additionally, JETT uses the <a href="http://jagg.sourceforge.net">jAgg</a> library
            (Java Aggregations) to perform aggregate operations, such as Sum and Average, and
            super-aggregation operations, such as rollups and cubes, and display the calculations
            in the spreadsheet.  It also uses jAgg to perform analytic operations, such as Lag,
            Lead, and RatioToReport.</p>
            <p>JETT allows the developer to follow the MVC pattern easily.  JETT is the Controller,
            the developer creates the Model, and either the developer or another party controls the
            Excel spreadsheet template, which acts as the View.</p>
            <p>To summarize JETT, the developer supplies an Excel spreadsheet <em>template</em>,
            which provides the structure, layout, and styling of the resultant spreadsheet.  Then,
            the developer creates <em>beans</em> that contain the actual data to be populated in
            the spreadsheet.  Finally, the developer uses an
            <a href="apidocs/net/sf/jett/transform/ExcelTransformer.html"><code>ExcelTransformer</code></a>,
            the JETT API entry point, to transform the template spreadsheet into the resultant
            spreadsheet, complete with the desired data, which can then be published.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="Main Features">
            <ul>
                <li>Integration with <a href="http://commons.apache.org/jexl/">Apache Commons JEXL
                    </a> 2.1.1 (Java Expression Language).  This allows for easy creation of
                    expressions that are substituted with model data in the form of beans at
                    runtime.</li>
                <li>Integration with <a href="http://poi.apache.org/">Apache POI</a> 3.12.  JETT is
                    built on top of the extensive Apache POI library with which it controls sheet
                    transformations.</li>
                <li>Integration with the SourceForge project
                    <a href="http://jagg.sourceforge.net">jAgg</a> 0.9.0.  JETT uses this library
                    to evaluate Aggregate Expressions, a JETT-based extension to JEXL that allows
                    aggregate expressions to be evaluated, such as Sum, Count, Avg, etc.</li>
                <li>Built-in Tag library that allows XML-like tags to be placed in template
                    spreadsheets, allowing such simple programming-like constructs as “if”, “for”,
                    “forEach”, and more.</li>
                <li>Looping tags support “copy down” and “copy right” behavior for the display of
                    Collections.</li>
                <li>Custom Tag Libraries may be coded and supplied to JETT for execution.</li>
                <li>Like Apache POI, JETT attempts as much as possible to keep existing Excel
                    features intact, including Charts, Macros, etc.</li>
                <li>The CellListener interface allows dynamic, custom processing of Cells, such as
                    alternate row highlighting, value manipulation, etc.</li>
                <li>Merged cell regions are shifted and copied as appropriate.</li>
                <li>Row heights and columns widths are respected as best as possible.</li>
                <li>Template sheets may be dynamically cloned and separately evaluated in the
                    resultant spreadsheet.</li>
                <li>Multiple collections may be implicitly processed using a single loop.</li>
                <li>It is possible to implement and display adjacent, or side-by-side, lists.</li>
                <li>Supports binary Excel (.xls) and XML Excel (.xlsx) documents.</li>
                <li>RichTextStrings are supported, even within Expressions.</li>
                <li>JETT gives access to POI Objects in JEXL Expressions, which in turn allows
                    access to Workbook and Sheet properties, including the Header &amp; Footer, and
                    PageSetup objects.</li>
                <li>Excel Formula generation support.</li>
                <li>JDBC Query Execution inside the template.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Requirements">
            <p>JETT requires the following libraries:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Apache POI 3.14</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>poi-3.14-20160307.jar</li>
                    <li>poi-ooxml-3.14-20160307.jar</li>
                    <li>poi-ooxml-schemas-3.14-20160307.jar</li>
                    <li>Apache POI, in turn, depends on the following library: XML Beans 2.6.0.</li>
                </ul>
                <li>XML Beans 2.6.0</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>xmlbeans-2.6.0.jar</li>
                </ul>
                <li>Apache Commons JEXL 2.1.1</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>commons-jexl-2.1.1.jar</li>
                    <li>Apache Commons JEXL 2.1.1 in turn depends on Commons Logging 1.1.1.</li>
                </ul>
                <li>Apache Commons Logging 1.2</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>commons-logging-1.2.jar</li>
                </ul>
                <li>SourceForge's jAgg 0.9.0</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>jagg-core-0.9.0.jar</li>
                </ul>
                <li>JUnit 4.8.2 (for testing only)</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>junit-4.8.2.jar</li>
                </ul>
                <li>HSQLDB 1.8.0.10 (for testing only)</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>hsqldb-1.8.0.10.jar</li>
                </ul>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>