<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Looping Tags</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Looping Tags">
            <p>JETT has several built-in looping tags.  These tags are used to display repeating
            content, such as indexed content or <code>Collections</code>.  Normally, the block's
            content is copied downward to display repeating content.  Other content that is below
            the block is shifted downward to make room.</p>
            <p>All looping tags are defined by classes that subclass the abstract class
            <code>BaseLoopTag</code>, which itself subclasses the abstract class
            <code>BaseTag</code>.  These are JETT's built-in looping tags:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="for.html">"for" tag</a></li>
                <li><a href="forEach.html">"forEach" tag</a></li>
                <li><a href="multiForEach.html">"multiForEach" tag</a></li>
            </ul>
            <p>All looping tags support several common attributes:</p>
            <h1>Attributes</h1>
            <ul>
                <li>All looping tags support all <a href="basics.html">base tag attributes</a>.</li>
                <li><strong>copyRight: Boolean</strong> Optional.  Normally, content below the
                block is shifted downward to make room for the copied blocks.  But if this
                attribute is true, then this will shift content to the right of the block out of
                the way, and the block will be copied to the right instead of downward.  Default:
                false (downward).</li>
                <li><strong>fixed: Boolean</strong> Optional.  If true, then the tag will
                assume that the proper space is present into which the blocks will be copied, so it
                will NOT shift other content out of the way to make room for the copied blocks.
                Default: false (shifting content out of the way will occur).</li>
                <li><strong>pastEndAction: String</strong> Optional.  If specified, then its value
                controls what happens to blocks when it is beyond the end of iteration on a
                <code>Collection</code>.  The circumstances that allow extra blocks beyond the end
                of a <code>Collection</code> are explained in the page for each looping tag, when
                they arise.  Here are the possible values:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><em>clear</em> This works just like the "elseAction" attribute of the
                    <a href="if.html">if tag</a>: remove the contents of the cells.
                    This is the default.</li>
                    <li><em>remove</em> This works just like the "elseAction" attribute of the
                    <a href="if.html">if tag</a>: remove the cells, including cell contents,
                    formatting, borders, and merged regions.</li>
                </ul>
                <li><strong>groupDir: String</strong> Optional.  This works just like the
                "groupDir" attribute of the <a href="group.html">group tag</a>: if specified, then
                JETT will create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the resultant rows or columns.
                Here are the possible values:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li><em>rows</em> Create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the resultant
                    rows.</li>
                    <li><em>cols</em> Create an Excel Group (Outline) out of the resultant
                    columns.</li>
                    <li><em>none</em> Do not create an Excel Group (Outline).  This is the default.</li>
                </ul>
                <li><strong>collapse: boolean</strong> Optional.  This works just like the
                "collapse" attribute of the <a href="group.html">group tag</a>: This determines
                whether the Excel Group (Outline) created is in a collapsed state.  The default is
                <code>false</code> (not collapsed).</li>
                <li><strong>onLoopProcessed: TagLoopListener</strong> Optional.  Specify a
                <code>TagLoopListener</code> that will be called every time a loop's processing has
                finished.  Alternatively, a fully-qualified Java class name may be specified here,
                and JETT will instantiate one, provided it has a no-argument public constructor.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>