<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="rgettman@users.sourceforge.net">Randy Gettman</author>
        <title>Name Tag</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The Name Tag">
            <p>During transformation, Excel named ranges may have their reference formulas changed
            using the "name" tag. This tag must be used in the bodiless form.  When processed, the
            "name" tag associates the given named range with a
            <a href="../expressions/jett_formulas.html">JETT formula</a>.  After transformation is
            complete, JETT formula processing recognizes that a named range is associated with the
            JETT formula, and it replaces the named range's formula with the proper Excel formula
            generated based on the JETT formula.  The "name" tag is used in an otherwise blank
            cell, and the end result is that the cell that contained the "name" tag is cleared of
            content.</p>
            <h1>Attributes</h1>
            <ul>
                <li>The "name" tag supports all <a href="basics.html">base tag attributes</a>.</li>
                <li><strong>name: String</strong> Required.  This is the name of the named range.</li>
                <li><strong>preferWorkbookScope: boolean</strong> Optional.  Excel supports the
                    concept of scope for named ranges, allowing the same named range name on
                    different scopes.  A scope can be for the entire workbook or for one particular
                    sheet.  A value of <code>true</code> here means that JETT will find a named
                    range in the workbook scope over one scoped to the sheet on which this tag is
                    found.  The default value is <code>false</code>, to prefer a named range scoped
                    to the current sheet over one scoped to the workbook.</li>
                <li><strong>formula: String</strong> Required.  A JETT formula (e.g. "$[SUM(B2)]")
                    that is to be associated with the given named range.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Example">
            <p>This example demonstrates how "name" tags work with named ranges and charts.  The
            chart has its series ranges referring to named ranges.  The "name" tags associate a
            JETT formula with the named ranges that are used by the chart.</p>
            <p>Here is the template.</p>
            <img src="../images/template_name1.gif" alt="Names Template"/>
            <p>The chart has one series, and its values are taken from "Employees!employee_salaries".
            The x-axis values are taken from "Employees!employee_names".  Note that it doesn't
            matter what the named ranges refer to in the template, because the "name" tags will
            cause their ranges to be overwritten by the JETT formulas.  But it does matter that
            the named ranges are created in the template.  The "name" tag won't create a named
            range; it will only modify the formula for an existing named range.</p>
            <p>This template gets transformed into...</p>
            <img src="../images/result_name1.gif" alt="Names Result"/>
            <p>No complicated "offset" formulas are needed to fool Excel into taking the proper
            ranges for the chart.  There is no need to hard-code the number of rows into the chart\
            series.  Here are the named ranges in the resultant spreadsheet:</p>
            <img src="../images/result_name2.gif" alt="Named Ranges"/>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>